<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>No interest beyond the principall or, The court camisado. By reduction of government to its primitive end and integrity, Rom. 13.4. The ruler is the minister of God to thee for good. Also, nevves from Scotland : or, the reasons examined of the warre threatned. May. 1. 1648. Imprimatur, Gilb. Mabbott.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E437_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863096</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863096</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161641</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161641)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 69:E437[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>No interest beyond the principall or, The court camisado. By reduction of government to its primitive end and integrity, Rom. 13.4. The ruler is the minister of God to thee for good. Also, nevves from Scotland : or, the reasons examined of the warre threatned. May. 1. 1648. Imprimatur, Gilb. Mabbott.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 [i.e. 14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Becke, and are to be sold in the Old Bayley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 14 misnumbered 10.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161641:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NO INTEREST Beyond the PRINCIPALL OR, The Court CAMISADO. By Reduction of Government to its primitive end and Integrity,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 13. 4.</bibl> 
               <p>The <hi>Ruler</hi> is the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>ALSO, NEVVES from SCOTLAND: OR, The REASONS Examined of the Warre THREATNED.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May.</hi> 1. 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Gilb. Mabbott.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>H. Becke,</hi> and are to be ſold in the <hi>Old Bayley.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161641:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161641:2"/>
            <head>No Intereſt beyond the Principall. <hi>OR,</hi> The Court Camiſado.</head>
            <p>IN the caſe of divorce, when it was put to Chriſt by the Phariſees to know his opinions in it, he being neither Scribe nor Phariſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. of no ſect nor faction, one that drive no deſigne but Gods; and that came to fulfill the law, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, ſends thoſe great doctors to Schoole, to the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive end and inſtitution of marriage, as it came immediatly from God, in innocency, when, and where all things were very good, as he that will taſte water purely muſt doe it at the fountain. But they not ſatisfied with this ſolution by way of juſtification, urge an old ſtatute Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which by its antiquity, authority, and uſage might (as they thought) <hi>v.</hi> 7) plead right of preſcription for that maſculine priviledge of putting away their wives. But Chriſt tels them, that Plant never grew in innocency, God grafted no ſuch Sience in the ſtocke of created nature, it was a muſhroome that grew out of nature corrupted. <hi>Moſes</hi> (ſaies he) bacauſe of the hardneſs of your hearts, ſuffered you to put away your wives, <hi>but from the beginning it was not ſo,</hi> as who ſay. It was indeed a politique law of conceſſion, but policy muſt not annull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, neither reaſon of ſtate, not laws municipal muſt croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with right reaſon, or the principles of entire nature. Therefore I, who am come to enlighten your judgements, and reforme your manners <hi>(Goſpell-properties)</hi> tell you againe that whatever your luſts and exorbitancies might occaſion <hi>Moſes</hi> to do, or enact, by way of connivance or permiſſion, that does not juſtifie the practiſe (though never ſo old, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received) to be lawful, but rather ſhew it to be unlawful,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161641:3"/>
becauſe that permiſſion varies from the firſt poſition or ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard given by God himſelf, the prime legiſlator, whither this caſe if rightly ſtated and argued muſt be reduced for ſolution, no authority binding above his, nor no law againſt his, though ſeemingly never ſo ſpecious.</p>
            <p>A cleare demonſtration, which is the beſt way to anſwer queſtions and work reformations in matters of Government. Not to be miſ-led by <hi>words of Art, civill ſuperſtition, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall pretences,</hi> to the violation of the lawes of God, nature, or reaſon. It is true that Government (as marriage) is of God, but it is as true that governors (as perſons marrying) are of men, and that the great Intereſt (which word is now the onely I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol that men ſal down and worſhip) of both Government and Governours is the glory of God, and the good of mankind: The end of the inſtitution is the onely intereſt of the thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and conſequently the Mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e-wand or Standard by which it is to be regulated and reduced, though as old as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> when God gives opportunity, and time brings truth to light. In this age of ours, Kings plead for prerogative, flowres of the Crown, and right of Soveraignty, as they and their flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers cal it. And even Parliament-priviledge is made uſe of by prerogative members, for promoting the arbitrary intereſt of the Crown; thus is authority wire-drawn, as if Governours rather then the Governed, were the end of Government, and Government it ſelfe is rather made a perſonall Intereſt, then a publique utility. Yea, Laws, nay Oathes, are thus made uſe of to captive &amp; inſnare men, by prerogative gloſſes, as if it wer in the power of men, who are the ſons of reaſon to ſwear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into beaſts, and to abjure their very nature, and that by vertue of an ordinance of God, which Government is. What confidence can Kings have in people by ſuch ties as being <hi>ex natura rei</hi> unlawfull, do untie themſelves, and which are both unlawful to be taken, and when taken unlawfull to be kept. Such gloſſes as Court Paraſites, put upon lawes allegiance tending to make Kings abſolute, and their power as well ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161641:3"/>
as poſitive, and their duty meere matters of pleaſure, and acts of will, in the way neither to render Kings ſafe, nor their people happy.</p>
            <p>The Popery of an implicit faith and blinde obedience, will not, cannot laſt alwayes; which becauſe it is ſo much coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by Epiſcopacy (that rag of Rome) therefore thence is that maxim. No Biſhops, no King, implying that when ever the vail of ignorance and blind obedience was done away by aboliſhing of Biſhops, and the peoples eyes were opened by divinity, and reaſon to ſee themſelves miſ-led by pretence of authority from a right underſtanding of the nature of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they will never endure to be ſlaves inſtead of freemen, ſubjects to governours inſtead of government, and to ſerve their intereſts who are their Miniſters and Gods meerly for their good, having their being (in office and authority) by, for, nor to no other end or purpoſe. For as the Pope is afraid of nothing ſo much as the tranſlating the word into popular languages for fear of betraying his jugling tricks in divinity, ſo nor Kings and Royalliſts then that the Lawes of the Land ſhould be Engliſh'd, I meane not ſo much in language, as in ſenſe and reaſon (though there is no good reaſon why Engliſh eyes ſhould look through French ſpectacles, except it be to ſee to loſe our way to liberty and property as they have done) but for Engliſh Lawes to ſpeake Prerogative, is worſe then to ſpeake French, ſome Commentators are better Courtiers then Lawyers, who ſhould be men of reaſon, and not ſo diſcredit the Law (the honour of their profeſſion) as to force it againſt reaſon to advance the will of a man above the reaſon of a State, and the originall end of government it ſelfe. Therefore its time to be no longer fool'd with State tearmes of <hi>Intereſt, Jewels, and Flowers of the Crowne,</hi> or the old over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worne word of <hi>Prerogative,</hi> for what is this but firſt to ſet up a golden image, and then to fall downe and worſhip it. I am not againſt Kings nor their Crownes, its the abuſe, and onely
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161641:4"/>
that that I abominate, which hath as much blindfolded the people of Chriſtendome, as the Popes ſupremacy hath the Princes thereof, whoſe eyes yet ſhall be opened to ſee their errour, and to withdraw their necks out of his Eccleſiaſticall yoake, and ſo its hoped ſhall the peoples (ſpecially Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) in things Civil; to know, as their obedience to authority, ſo good authority in reaſon, juſtice, and equity, for that their obedience; for ſo men act like men, elſe like beaſts, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ſubjected to will, which yet is not the leaſt part of that bondage of corruption the creation groans and travels in pain under, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 20, 21, 22. being unwillingly made ſubject to that vanity, in hope and earneſt expectation to be delivered: and ſhal we be ſo vaine, ſpecially when a price is new put into our hands, as willingly to take up that yoake which the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though ſenſeleſſe and irrationall, unwillingly beares, in hope of being infranchiſed of it at the laſt, accounting even annihilation better then ſubordination to the inordinate will of falne mankinde. Old errours are ſo much cryed up under new lights, as that old truths will ſcarce be believed againſt cuſtome in errour: Kings they will not, but tell you its a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their intereſt not to be arbitrary, and the people they dare not believe it if the Princes doe not, though neither to 'ne nor to 'ther, but muſt needs grant that <hi>ab initio non fuit ſic,</hi> its conſonant neither to the nature, nor the end of government; and conſequently not of Sovereignty, which onely ſo farre is <hi>ſovereigne</hi> as it is <hi>preſervative.</hi> Therefore the Law ſayes (of al men) the King can doe no wrong, hath leſſe power to doe wrong, becauſe greater obligation to doe right then any man elſe; nay he is ſo far from having power to doe wrong, that he is neither to doe it, nor ſuffer it to be done by any inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our powers, but to ſee that juſtice and protection according to Law be adminiſtred to all by the Miniſters thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee's the chiefe.</p>
            <p>But the nature, of man even in innocency (though not by it)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161641:4"/>
luſteth after an exorbitant ſuperiority, for when God had made him Lord over all but the forbidden fruit, hee thought himſelfe no King over the creature whilſt the Creator limited his power, though but in one, and therefore he reſolves either to win the horſe, or loſe the ſaddle, gaine that, or loſe all. So Kings, bee their power never ſo great <hi>to doe,</hi> yet except they may alſo have power <hi>to undoe,</hi> negative as well as poſitive, power to deny, as well as to grant, and undoe as well as doe, they are unſatisfied, and ſticke not in effect to affirme, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you grant them <hi>Tyranny,</hi> you oppoſe <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Wherein yet they doe themſelves no right, nor thoſe that flatter them into ſuch principles: for when people ſee they cannot grant ſafe and lawfull premiſes, but with hazzard of ſophiſtical and prevaricate concluſions to bee inferred thereupon, it makes them fearefull to grant any thing, leſt they loſe all, an Inch gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, makes an Ell taken. As if commiſſions, &amp;c. for honour-ſake goe in the Kings name, then the Court conſequence is, they are the act, not his Laws; then the next reſult is, they are <hi>ad placitum,</hi> and not <hi>quamdiu bene ſe geſſerint,</hi> Prerogative is ſo procreant that no wombe is barren to the third or fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, but every inference is productive of another. So let him have the honour to confirme and aſſert Laws; then the next remove is, you muſt allow him the uſe of his reaſon, and the next to that, therefore a negative as well as an affirmative voice: grant-freewill, and falling from Grace will follow. Suppoſe him the fountaine of honour; then, he retorts, I may conferre it on whom I pleaſe, and for what cauſe, for vice as well as vertue. I may make <hi>George Villiers</hi> and his vertuous mother, Duke and Counteſſe of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and court-mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions Privy-councellours, nay aliens of the Scotch Nation, (whoſe native ſtate intereſt by vicinity, is againſt ours) Peers and Parliamentmen in England. Therefore lay the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the rocke, not in the ſands: make out that poſition in plain Engliſh, That <hi>the King can do no wrong,</hi> nor the <hi>Crown</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161641:5"/>
neither, by declaring that neither legally nor illegally by abuſed law, or power above law, it neither is, nor ought to be in their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to do ſo, and provide accordingly, let <hi>legall</hi> and <hi>regall</hi> be but one and the ſame, as in ſound, ſo in a ſafe and ſound ſence, univocall tearmes: and ſoveraignty made ſoveraigne by preferring <hi>the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Oath,</hi> with a right underſtanding; <hi>Magna Charta</hi> purged of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; and the <hi>Petition of Right</hi> well back'd with <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> to be principall flowers of the Crowne before it be worne againe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that by a penall law: for if it be lawfull for a private man or particular ſubject to implead his Prince by law upon a particular wrong, much more for the State, or people in generall to implead him by armes, or proceed againſt him in caſe of a generall wrong, when theirs, neither Law nor Judge, but <hi>ſalus popoli</hi> to determine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them. And therefore <hi>Trajan</hi> both wiſely and worthily, when hee delivered the ſword to the <hi>Pretor,</hi> bid him uſe it for him whilſt he ruled well, and againſt him, when ill.</p>
            <p>Let Kings have as much honour, freedome, and ſafety in the way of righteouſnes as becomes men of their place, the contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is diſhonour, ſlavery and danger both to Prince and people: Let the people know that his name is of no more uſe in commiſſions and ſtatutes, then his Image and ſuperſcription upon coyn, the one argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more propriety or title in him then the other, the honour of both his is &amp; that for publik advantage, not diſadvantage, he can no more ſuſpend the one, then the other, or deſtitute his people either of laws or their lawful execution, then of money and trade. Goſpel timeſhould make our Kings better Chriſtians, then to deſire ſuch Catholike authority, when they ſee, heare, and read the evill effects that doe, and cannot but attend it, both to him that is in authority by way of temptation, and thoſe that are under authority by way of ruine and deſtruction. Giants of old, thoſe men-monſters begotten of Gods diſpleaſure, &amp; inordinate concupiſcence, what effects had their exorbitancy of ſtrength but to make them men of exorbitant minds? proud &amp; cruel, rebellious toward God, and tyrannous over men. A rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſize beſt befits a reaſonable man, too much power of any kind makes a man a monſter, and hazzards him to do monſtrous things. <hi>Nimrod</hi> was the firſt we read of, that by invaſion and oppreſſion of publique right and liberty affected a <hi>Babell</hi> Kingdome Government beyond rule, and to be abſolute on earth as God is in heaven, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was he call'd <hi>The mighty hunter before the Lord, Gen.</hi> 10. 8, 9, 10. And every one after him that hunted inordinatly after power, as he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161641:5"/>
did, was proverbially called as he was, another <hi>Nimrod,</hi> or (as wee now ſay) <hi>Nimrod</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Nimrod</hi> the third, <hi>the mighty hunter</hi> &amp;c. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving both his name and ſtile, as the brand of his preſumption, and unlawfull ambition or uſurpation. The account that Kings are to make for the talents that are lawfully conferred upon them is great enough, and need not be increaſed by the talents themſelves unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſurped. Abuſed power makes men on earth, the moſt unlike to God in heaven of any thing, therfore unlimitted authority is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible to a creature, and able to make a man a devill. Angels in heaven as well as <hi>Adam</hi> in paradiſe, fell by free-will and freewill power, and how then think we can Common-wealths ſtand by it, ſpecially in one man? That King that makes conſcience of his place and people, will rather think his power too much then too little, conſidering he muſt anſwer for no more then he hath, and with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> be content to depart of his ſpirit to leſſen his charge for his own eaſe, and their benefit; and if he doe not, then a little is too much, for power without conſcience is like a horſe without a bridle, ready to hurry the rider into ruine, and over-run al that ſtands in his way. Nor will a conſcientious King purchaſe power over his people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wills, with the loſſe of their blood, his greater care will be to uſe that well he hath, and not to make his ſucceſſors abſolute, that his Subjects may be ſlaves, nor conquer whom he ſhould protect, he will as well remember that he is the father of his Country, as of his next Heire, who yet is but his ſucceſſor, and the Kingdoms Heire, the Crown and Kingdome being an incorporate body, for he cannot diſ-inherit him, though the people may, and upon miſ-government depoſe him, as in caſe of adultery marryed people may divorce, the knot that ties them together, being broken aſunder: his care ſhould be rather to leave rules to his Son to govern well, then power to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern ill: and himſelf to dye deſired, as good <hi>Joſiah</hi> did, rather then when he is dead, to be ſtiled <hi>of happy memory,</hi> becauſe of his unhappy Reigne. Would Kings be more Religious, they would be leſſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, and ſee reaſon for it; yea, beleeve themſelves as well in debt to their people, as their people to them, owing both mutuall love and duty, ſtriving rather to deſerve obedience then to inforce it, and entituling themſelves to their peoples Allegiance rather by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations then commands, themſelves inviolably keeping the Oath of good Government, that ſo they may not give their people the leaſt coulour of liberty, to breake the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of dutifull Allegiance, and knowing how dangerous a thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Printe is both in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161641:6"/>
the ſad conſequence of ill example, and the woſull effects of divine juſtice, ſo frequently inflicted on the people either for or by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Princes ſins.</p>
            <p>What reaſon can be given why all other Governors and Magiſtrats are to rule for the publique good, and onely Kings for their owne greatning? No inferior authority hath a negative power to ſuſpend juſtice or protection ſo farre as he is to adminiſter it by his place, the King himſelf can derive no ſuch power to any, and if he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive it, then he hath it not inherent in himſelf, for the Soveraignes power is principally to impower others. <hi>Magis</hi> and <hi>Minus</hi> make no eſſentiall difference; Betwixt the King and a Conſtable there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of power in point of proportion, but not in <hi>ſpecie</hi> or kind, it is of the ſame kinde, and to the ſelf-ſame end, one hath not power for, and the other againſt. Or what reaſon can be ſhowne, why the King ought to have a negative arbitrary power? is it becauſe Kings are more infallible, &amp; unerring then other men? we have not found it ſo. Or what good reaſon can be ſhown that <hi>de facto</hi> he hath it? Hath any known law of the Land conferred it on him, or is it meerly by uſurpation? hath he taken it becauſe the people durſt not deny it, as former Kings have done Forreſt-Lands, &amp; then made the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe them by forreſt-Laws: why then, preſcription in wrong, entitles no man to right, eſpecially Kings, whoſe office is neither to do, nor ſuffer to be done, any wrong to the body whereof they are the head. Or is it as ſome affirme, becauſe the King is ſupreame? for ſay they, ſeeing arbitrary power muſt be ſomewhere, therfore it is fitteſt to be in the ſupreme Magiſtrate. To this I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That arbitrary Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative power is in the ſupreme Magiſtracy or Government, not Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour; the Parliament, not the King; for the people being a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous diſperſed multitude, and ſo not fit alwayes to be together, to ſee to the execution of their own Laws, do therefore meet occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in an aggregate body, for the conſultive, and creative part of Laws, and conſtitutions, that ſo they may be ſuch as are moſt fit, and doe beſt ſute with the nature of the place and people; and then leave them for the executive part principally to the care of the King, with other ordained Miniſters, as being better executed by a few then a many, and better conſulted and made by a many then a few; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he the honor of Sword &amp; Scepter, and for that cauſe were good Kings in former times wont to goe their progreſſes, as Judges doe their circuits, not to make hunting-matches, &amp; horſe-races, nor yet to give Laws, but to inquire and countenance the execution of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161641:6"/>
juſtice, &amp; preſervation of peace, according to law, &amp; puniſh the violators</p>
            <p>And as Kings, ſo all other Governments and governors, their Intereſt is neither contrary to, nor diverſe from the publick good, their chief end is their cheif intereſt, neither power, priviledge, nor liberty to conſult, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, or conclude, belongs to any (and to them leaſt that are intruſted moſt) but what hath proximity with, is reductive to, and acted for, it; therfore thoſe Parliament-men whoſe principles and tranſactions vary from that pole, they are the moſt deſtructive members to Parliament-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that drive a Court deſigne with publick imployment, for Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Priviledge run the ſame danger, the apparent abuſe of ſame brings all into queſtion; <hi>potius unus quam unitas,</hi> better then throw out ſome rotten Apples, then ſpoyle the whole hoard; be not tenderer of your members then they are true to their truſt, if the Common wealth ſee ſome made examples, the puniſhment of a few, will preſerve the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole, that the body is ſound, though ſome members be rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: God made not man for himſelf, the intereſt of the creature, is the ſervice of his Creator, and therefore our riſe was our fall, the raiſing of our intereſt, was the ruine of us all. He that being choſen and intruſted with arbitrary power, wil therfore uſe it arbitrarily, is <hi>Adams</hi> own child, and after his likeneſſe. If it be objected, that the King pretends the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt in thoſe things which by abſolute power he claimes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles himſelf unto, as the <hi>Militia,</hi> and negative voyce; that they are for the better protecting and rule of his people, and the Royall party in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, forſooth, urge Liberty of conſcience, for liberty of ſpeech, <hi>Cum Privilegio,</hi> to betray their truſt. To theſe I Anſwer, firſt Joyntly: That it is an eaſie matter to put a bait upon a hook, and no hard thing to catch Gudgins with it, but for my part I will never truſt him, nor them, by the <hi>By,</hi> that erre in the main. Secondly, Severally, And firſt for the Kings claim and pretences (which the effects have proved barely to be ſuch) in reaſon he can neither deſire it, if he know himſelf to be but man, nor his people grant it, to his, &amp; their apparent ruine. Only blind <hi>Cupid</hi> is fit to ſtand a top of the wheel of <hi>Fortune,</hi> none that have eyes in their heads would deſire ſo ſlippery a place, when they ſee they ſo much over top themſelves that their hands cannot mannage what is under their feet, but they muſt needs turn round to their own ruine. But if <hi>ſeeing they ſee not,</hi> and will venture their necks to have their wills, yet there is no reaſon the people ſhould build <hi>Babel</hi> to bring confuſion upon themſelves. <hi>VViſdom</hi> is, to purſue a right end by right means, conſequently, not to expect good government from a corrupt will, endowed with Arbitrary power. What hath bin the ruin of <hi>Empire,</hi> ſo much as <hi>Empire?</hi> Kings have lived to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent their power, and people much more.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:161641:7"/>
            <p>And Secondly, for his party in the Parliament Priviledge in their hands is as bad as prerogative in his, they having no more right of power to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe that, then he this. Whoever repreſents a County or Corporation is entruſted by a part of member of the Common-wealth for the good of the whole, and is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of an Embaſſador or Commiſſioner to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate in a joynt body with the States Generall, for the State in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. For by the Laws of Embaſſie, State agents (though Plenipotentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) are not to betray them they treat for, their power is neither inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor ought to be interpreted to the prejudice but profit of them that imploy them. The <hi>Feffee</hi> for the <hi>Feffor.</hi> Liberty and priviledge are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to tranſact the liberty, property, and ſafety of the people, and he that goes retrograde to thoſe, what place or part of the Common-wealth ſoever he ſerve for, by right of community ought to be rejected by the reſt that ſerve for, and are intruſted with the whole.</p>
            <p>In a word, words by tract of time degenerate like men. <hi>Tirannus</hi> once was taken in the better part, when Kings were better common-wealths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and that they and their people were joynt purchaſers, trading abroad &amp; not at home, for preeminence. So was the word <hi>Intereſt,</hi> whilſt it was of publick cognizance, and all <hi>Qu. Elizabeths</hi> dayes kept it ſelf ſober by drinking <hi>Engliſh Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re</hi> till it was made drunk with <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>tiniack,</hi> and the King and his Courtiers by <hi>uſe</hi> upon <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> upon <hi>intereſt</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſwallowed up all, the peoples <hi>Principall.</hi> And <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelf run haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to have her eyes put out, that <hi>Prapria que maribus,</hi> which was wont to be the common name for all men, it begun to be wholly ingroſſed at Court, entailed upon the crown &amp; begg'd for a Monopoly, inſomuch as there was almoſt no Reaſon left but <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> within the compaſſe of a cabinet councell, all elſe was either bruitiſh or rebell on, nor no ſtate but that of the King &amp; his Royal conſort, the one <hi>Scatch,</hi> the other <hi>French.</hi> When publick <hi>Intereſt</hi> is impropriated <hi>ex officia,</hi> to private &amp; perſonall purpoſes, then ceaſeth the name &amp; nature of a Governour by deviating from the primitive end &amp; inſtitution of government, ordain'd by God &amp; Nature; &amp; conſequently love, loyalty, obedience, duty: for what oblieges theſe? not greatnes without goodnes, for then the devil might challenge them at our hands, who by Scripture is ſtiled <hi>principalities and powers,</hi> yea, <hi>the Prince of this world.</hi> Authority (whatever the kind or ſpecies of it be) whileſt it points right to the pole, and retains the vertue of the Lord-ſtone, where with it was firſt touched, its ſafe to ſale by it, but if either through corruption, or injury of time, it make ſtanding variations at wrong points, then it muſt either be new touched, or quite changed elſe contrary to intention, when firſt ſea-ſaile, youle make a wrong voyage, and fall amongſt enemies inſtead of friends; or a deſtructive, and be caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt rock; and ſands inſtead of knowne Seas.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:161641:7"/>
            <head>NEWES from SCOTLAND OR Their reaſons examined of the WARRE threatned.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Scots would faine make war upon</hi> England, <hi>but they are to ſeeke for a</hi> why and a wherefore; <hi>and are ready to fall together by the eares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves what ſhall be the cauſe of the quarrell (yet keep us in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall alarme to the loſſe of</hi> Ireland) <hi>for the world muſt have a</hi> blind. <hi>But bee the reaſon never ſo politicke, Religion muſt be the overture; which the Scotch dangerous Committee not being wiſe enough to reconcile,</hi> Traquire <hi>who of late was firſt in their exception, and now in acceptation) was called to councell to help at a dead lift, being for michiavillian policy another</hi> Strafford.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One part of them ſay the Sectaries (meaning the Army) have broken the Covenant,</hi> which they never tooke.) <hi>But if breach of Covenant be a cauſe of quarrell, the Scots neede not goe ſo farre to fight, they have Covenant brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers nearer hand at home; is it poſſible that ſuch pretenders to piety ſhould ſee a moat in their brothers eye ſo far off, and overlooke the beame that is in their own, ſtreyne at a gnat, and ſwallow a camel, threaten warre to</hi> England, <hi>for they themſelves know not what; one while ſaying the Covenant is broken, and another while that it is endangered; and the whilſt cocker up their owne Commiſſioners with an</hi> omne bene, <hi>in their palpable Covenant-breaches and Apoſtacies. But it ſeemes they muſt fall out with us, to keep them friends amongſt themſelves; though if they had eyes in their heads, they might ſee Gods hand in creating ſuch fewds at home, to prevent the miſchiefe they would bring abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But wherein have the Army broken the Covenant? why principally for not being Presbyterians, for that in pretence with ſome, and reality with others, is made the chiefe, if not the only hinge that the Covenant winds and turnes upon, though the word Presbitery is not ſo much as once named in the Covenant, a weak foundation then to build a warre upon; but to ſtrengthen it, they ſay the Army have refuſed orders for their disbanding, and forced orders for their ſtanding (though the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>never told them ſo) but they forget what their Army did when it was ſent to but to disband their ſupernumeraries, which they flatly refuſed, and forcibly kept them a foot ſpite of the Parliament, and to the deſpite of the poor Country, that groaned under ſo heavy a burden of ſo heavy a body; and by the ſame force kept</hi> Carlile <hi>and</hi> Newcaſtle, <hi>whether the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would or no (by what clauſe in the Covenant or Treaty, is not knowne to this day) and the King of</hi> England <hi>too, in</hi> England, <hi>till they thought good to part with him, and that notwithſtanding all authority, reaſon or right to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary But the true reaſon why the Army (whoſe greateſt fault in their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe) is ſuch an eye ſore, it is becauſe by their meanes principally
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161641:8"/>
their ſtrong party in</hi> England <hi>is much weakned, thoſe fine deſignes of a joynt intereſt, legiſlative propriety, and the Kings comming to</hi> London <hi>in freedome, honour, and ſafety, and other ſuch like, have been ſhrewdly diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by demoliſhing their eleven pillars, and line of communication at once. If the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>and their Army, were as miſchievouſly diſpoſed as they would render them, and did beleeve breach of Covenant, cauſe of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, they would never ſit ſtill, and ſuffer ſuch retrogradation as is daily, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively acted in</hi> Scotland, <hi>from the Kingdoms, to the Kings Cauſe and Party, covenanted and fought againſt; nor their Committee of danger to denounce warre as they do: having a viſible power on foote, to ſpoile their councels before they can bring them to maturity, and to fetch back what they carried hence, and thoſe Engliſh Malignants and Incendiaries that went hence, which contrary to Covenant they refuſe to deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brotherly love and charity covers a multitude of faults, and does not cry every failer for a breach of Covenant on neither ſide (no more than every diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is a breach of wed-locke) eſpecially touching things of non-concernment and a Covenant ſo large, comprehenſive, and ſubject in many things, to various ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptations by its manner of penning.</hi> David <hi>in the</hi> 44. Pſalme <hi>ſhewes what God counts breach of Covenant, when hee ſaith,</hi> verſ. 17, 18. <hi>We have not dealt</hi> falſly <hi>in thy Covenant: our heart is not</hi> turned backe. <hi>Now whether in this ſenſe the Lord</hi> Louden <hi>or the Lord</hi> Fairfax, <hi>the Scotch Papers and Practiſes, or the Parliaments declarations and long ſufferings have broken Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, let God and the World judge. As the Covenant warrants not breaking ſo nor fighting for breaking (much leſſe a ſuppoſed one, and that in our own forme and intereſt) God is witneſſe as of the Covenant ſo of the breach, and it proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongs to him, not man to puniſh, ſave in their ſeverall</hi> places, vocations and intereſts, <hi>thoſe are the words of the Covenant, whereby the</hi> Scotiſh <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, may and ought to queſtion their owne</hi> Scotch <hi>Covenant-breakers, but by no means to ſtretch their line over</hi> Tweed, <hi>and to make themſelves work in anothers Harveſt, to puniſh us and not themſelves, for things concerning us, not them. But it ſeems when the Covenant was firſt made in</hi> Scotl. <hi>it was then reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſhould be broke in</hi> England, <hi>and that whatſoever was acted croſſe to their deſignes, eſpecially of joynt intereſt, ſhould be the breach of it, elſe they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring in ſuch farre fetch'd unconcerning things into the account, as they do. When they have done juſtice in</hi> Scotland, <hi>upon their apoſtalized Covenanters, Malignants, and Incendiaries, we in</hi> England <hi>will thanke them for their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and friendly animadverſions in what they can juſtly taske us or probably ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect us, of what kind, but not till then, nor further then that. For by the Covenant the ſupream judicatories of both Kingdoms</hi> reſpectively <hi>have only power to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh. Another party are angry and threaten warre becauſe wee will not receive the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161641:8"/>
King upon their tearmes, and let them exerciſe a legiſlative power (ſo furiouſly driven on) here in</hi> England, <hi>for which they alſo urge the Covenant (that</hi> Scotch Magna Charta) <hi>which becauſe they made it, therefore they conceive they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not breake it, aſſuming a legiſlative power not onely in, but over poore</hi> England <hi>by vertue of it, for that they that are the makers, muſt it ſeems be interpreters, and thus the Covenant which was intended by us unto liberty, was meant and is made uſe of by them unto our bondage; and the King</hi> his very party and cauſe <hi>Covenanted for, that was Covenanted and fought againſt,</hi> Monſtrum horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. <hi>An ounce of</hi> Scotiſh <hi>confidence is more worth than a pound of</hi> Engliſh <hi>honeſty. Thus</hi> Traquier <hi>himſelf is become a Covenanter: Such gameſters will never loſe, what game ſoever they play at, that can play faſt and looſe, and make any thing of every thing; and from the words,</hi> mutuall advice and conſent <hi>mentioned in the eigth Article of the</hi> Treaty <hi>intitle themſelves to a joynt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. and us to breach of Covenant and Treaty; whereas thoſe words imply on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus much, that as the war was managed by a joynt ingagement againſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy to both Nations, ſo that it ſhould not be ended by a peace tranſacted or treated by one Nation alone, without the privity and conſent of the other, that ſo neither of their intereſts might be damnified. Not that both of them ſhould be confounded. The rare contradictions that their Papers, and Practiſes hold forth; ſometimes the King muſt not come to</hi> London <hi>till he have given ſecurity and ſatisfaction, then again be muſt come without either; ſometimes propoſitions and no perſonall treaty, othertimes a perſonall treaty and no propoſitions; which now are impoſitions; ſometimes the King muſt take the Covenant, otherwhile if be come not to the length of our deſires, in ſo doing, we muſt be content; ſometimes they tell the King upon his refuſing the Propoſitions both Kingdomes will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained (for their mutuall ſafety) to agree and ſettle Religion and Peace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him; and then upon turne of the tide they tell us we muſt wait till God change his heart: For the ſafety of the Kingdome the Army muſt be Disbanded, and the King inveſted in the Militia, or it in him. Sure</hi> Janus <hi>is</hi> Propitious <hi>to theſe ambidexers, elſe they could never ſo bewitch wiſe men as well as fools with their Sorceries as they doe, and with the Preshyterian</hi> Eele-hooke <hi>draw the City and Aſſembly after them, and that not onely in</hi> England, <hi>but in</hi> Scotland <hi>alſo, where (they ſay) they have deluded the well-meaning Clergy, who are conſented to joyn with thoſe Covenant-breakers in a warre againſt us, provided it be for Covenant-breaking. The little good that we have got, by the great c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills that we have undergon, God juſtly may, and it may be will puniſh us for it, but they for their diſſembling ſhal not ſcape, hypocriſie and falſehood is as hateful to God as to man. I doubt not but the iſſue will prove it ſo, according to their own prayer or forme of thanksgiving upon their deliverance from the</hi> French <hi>by the aid of the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>in theſe words</hi>—Suffer us never O Lord to fall to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161641:9"/>
that Ingratitude, and deteſtable unthankefullnes, that we ſhall ſeek the deſtruction and death of thoſe, whom thou haſt made Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to deliver us from the tyranny of mercileſſe ſtrangers. Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate thou the councells of ſuch, as deceitfully travell to ſtirre the hearts of the inhabitants of either Realm againſt the other let their malitious practiſes be their owne confuſion.—<hi>But that which I admire is, that they ſhould joyn and unite in</hi> Scotland, <hi>to get</hi> England, <hi>(though with hazzard of their owne) and that wee will not do the like to keepe it, are wee ſo ſtout ſtomacked, and our malice ſo implacable, that we will rather loſe a good land than ſhake hands and be friends amongst our ſelves. I meane not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Cavaliers (thoſe excrements of</hi> Engliſh-men) <hi>of whom I dare prophecy they ſhall never hurt any but themſelves, nor doe much more harme (though they may often attempt it) then break glaſſe windows, and write libellous pamphlets) but the miſ-underſtanding City and Clergy, who doe well to oppoſe errour, ſo be that they themſelves erre not fundamentally in doing ſo, and cauſe the loſſe of all, or hazzard it, who have ſmal cauſe to think, they that are for the King will be for Presbytery. I am no</hi> Independent <hi>(ſave as to the</hi> Scots) <hi>but an Engliſh-man, were all of us ſo, true to Engliſh principles, and intereſt, as the Scots are to theirs, they durſt never ſet foot upon Engliſh ground in a war-like way. See we not how it hath been their conſtant practiſe and indeavor to ſet</hi> England <hi>on fire, that they might come in by the light of it, and ſhall we by our differences pave them a way, and open them a two leaved doore to enter in at, and march into the bowels of our Kingdome by, have we fought for the freedome of ourſelves and poſterity, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it as a brand out of the fire, to be cheated out of it at the laſt? What made this Kingdome bee ſo often conquered, from the</hi> Romans <hi>to the</hi> Normans, <hi>but domeſticke differences, and ſhall it now be our fate to become conquerable by thoſe we our ſelves have ſo often conquered, through diſ-union.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beleeve not their overtures, be they never ſo ſpecious, Thei'le tell you thei'le not joyne with Malignants and Cavaliers (as the King and the Earle of</hi> New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle <hi>gave out they would not joyn with Papiſts) whereas they do not only already receive the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; joyn with them, but themſelves are ſuch, faced quit about to the King and his cauſe, whereof they have given theſe good ſignes amongſt others, they have received Commiſſion from him to make</hi> Malignant <hi>Knights and Lords, that ſit in their Parliament, and to gratifie the King again have retorted</hi> Traquier <hi>and imployed him as a confiding man, in Embaſſie to the</hi> King <hi>in the Iſle of</hi> Wyght <hi>beleeving the King will give more credit to him that hath been true to his principles, then to them that are falſe to theirs</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
